If you think you know something but
don't write it down, you only think you
know it.
>> This is Leslie Lamport. He's a Turing
Award winner famous for his
contributions to distributed systems.
And I interviewed him for the stories
behind his papers.
>> Their reaction shocked me. They became
angry. I really thought they might
physically attack me.
>> What was it about Dystra's old solution
that you felt was unsatisfactory? It was
not an obvious idea to most people that
had actually impressed Dystra.
>> As the inventor of the Paxus algorithm,
I asked them his thoughts on the
competing raft algorithm.
>> There was a bug discovered in Raft and
fixed, but I believe the algorithm that
they found more understandable was one
with that bug.
>> I also enjoyed reflecting over his
50-year career. You say things like,
"You never considered yourself smart.
How could that be?" Stupid people think
they're smart because they're too stupid
to realize they're not.
>> You felt like a failure at some point
because you wanted to develop this grand
theory of concurrency and you never
discovered it. Do you still feel that
way?
Here's the full episode.
I wanted to start with the bakery
algorithm. What is the problem that the
bakery algorithm solves? And you know
how did you discover the problem?
>> Well uh the problem was invented or
discovered by Edkar Dystra in a 1965 I
think it was 1965 paper and that began I
consider that really the beginning of
the theory of uh concurrency concurrent
programming. He was the first one who
really
made use of the idea of of concurrency
as a way of structuring programs as a as
a collection of semi-independent tasks
and the processes have to uh synchronize
with one another. Uh one of the
processes or you know among the
processes would be well this was in the
days of time sharing uh you know right
at really at the beginning of beginnings
of time sharing and the idea of multiple
people using the same computer. People
realized that computers were worked
faster than humans and so and computers
were very expensive in those days. So uh
they wanted they could use a computer to
simultaneously
to be used simultaneously by multiple
people. The program that each user was
running you know was a separate program
but sometimes you know there were
resources that got shared. for example,
a printer, two people trying to print on
the same printer at the same time. Well,
the result would be, you know, not very
satisfactory. So uh he realized there
was this problem of uh synchronizing
um multiple processes via the idea of
what he called a critical section or
some piece of code in each of the
processes so that at most one process
can be executing that piece of code at
any particular time. So that code might
be the code that prints something on the
printer. So the problem was how to get
the uh processes to synchronize among
themselves so that at most one process
was executing its critical section at a
time. And
um it was in 1972 that I learned about
the problem because there was an article
giving a solution to it um in the CACM
communications of the ACM
and uh I mean I used to program and I
liked little programming problems you
know uh and this was just a very nice
little programming problem.
And so I looked at the solution, which
is fairly complicated, and I said, "Oh,
gee, that shouldn't be so hard." And so
I whipped off a very simple uh algorithm
for two processes and submitted it to
CACM. And a couple of weeks later, I
received uh a letter from the editor uh
pointing out the bug in my program. So
that had two effects.
The first was that I realized that
concurrent programs were hard to get
right and that you needed a proof that
they were correct. And second uh was
that made me feel I'm gonna solve that
damn problem. And I came up with the
bakery algorithm which was inspired by
uh the idea came from you know what now
called the deli problem where you have a
deli counter and that collects you know
tickets a roll of tickets and every
customer would come in and take a ticket
and then the the next person s to to be
served would be the one with the highest
the lowest numbered ticket uh that
hadn't been served yet. And basically
that I took that idea uh but since uh
there was no central server uh or at
least the the problem is as specified by
Dystra involved no central control. Each
process basically had to choose their
own ticket. That was you know the basic
idea and the algorithm was you know
quite simple. And I wrote a a proof of
correctness.
And uh the proof of correctness revealed
to me that
this algorithm was had this very
interesting property.
There was a general feeling in fact
somebody published in a in a book or
paper saying you know that it was
impossible to implement mutual exclusion
like this without using some lower level
mutual exclusion.
And the way most the mutual exclusion
that was assumed generally was that of
shared registers. you know, shared
pieces of memory that could be written
and write and uh read by different
processes. And the idea is that, you
know, you couldn't have one process, you
know, two processes writing at the same
time or one process reading while the
other process was writing. People
assumed that those actions were atomic.
They always performed as if they
occurred in some specific order. But the
amazing thing about the bakery algorithm
was that it didn't require that
assumption. It it used uh each shared
memory a piece of memory was only
written by a single process. So it
didn't have to worry about two processes
interfering with each other. The only
problem that you might come is that
somebody reading the uh value while it
was being written might get you know
some unknown value but the algorithm
worked anyway.
If somebody read if one process read
while the registers was being written
that process reading process could get
absolutely any value and the algorithm
still worked. I saw in your your writing
about this problem that you shared it
with a colleague named Anatol Hol and
the proof was so remarkable that uh they
didn't believe it and
>> well the the result was so remarkable.
>> Yes. Yes. that didn't believe it.
>> And uh you know I wrote the proof on the
on the
whiteboard for him and you know he
couldn't find it but he went home and
saying there must be something wrong
with it and uh he obviously never found
anything wrong with it.
>> Right. I saw the name of the paper is a
new solution of Dystra's concurrent
programming problem.
What was it about Dystra's old solution
that you felt was unsatisfactory and
made you want to solve this problem?
>> Uh well, there was an unsatisfactory
aspect of his original solution that had
the property that if there were a lot of
if processes kept trying to uh enter
their critical section uh an individual
process might be starved. might never
get access to to the critical section
that was solved uh by you know the next
solution I think was Don Kuth's the
condition that was
desired or that that measured that what
was considered the uh the efficiency of
it was how long a process might have to
wait and I believe that the bakery
algorith of them was the first one that
was really first come first served. That
is if one process came if what it meant
is if one process chose its number
before another process tried to enter
the first process would enter the
critical section before the other
process did. And I believe the bakery
algorithm was the first one with that uh
with that property. And also I think it
was simpler than uh other uh solutions
>> in a lot of the writing. I see that you
worked with Dystra and I saw in 1976
you actually worked for a month in the
Netherlands and you worked with them.
Can you talk about that a little bit?
>> Dyster used to had the things they're
called EWDs his initials.
little papers, things that when he he
thought of something, had some idea, he
would write it down and send it out to
people. Well, one of those EWDs was
about he and uh some
associates or actually sort of mentees I
guess you would call them wrote this
this algorithm. It was the first
concurrent garbage collection algorithm.
a way of writing programs evolved where
there was a pool of memory
uh that when a program would need a
piece of memory, it would ask some
server for it and be given this piece of
memory. Uh but at some point it would
stop using that memory. But the program
itself wouldn't know that the one the
particular process that created this
memory you know wouldn't know whether
some other process is using that memory
or not. So there was an additional
process called the garbage collector
which would go around examining the
memory and decide which pieces of memory
were no longer being used and then put
them back on the it's called the free
list and in which uh the uh server that
the process that was giving out the uh
uh memory would be able to to take it. I
looked at it and I realized that uh I
could simplify the algorithm. Uh because
he had some some spe the the handling of
the free list was done by a special
process that you know which had it to
worry about its own coordination with
the uh uh the processes that were using
the memory. And I realized that that
free list could just be made part of the
regular data structure.
uh so it didn't need special handling
and that seemed to me like a very uh
simple idea and a very obvious idea and
I sent it to him and then when I get got
the next version of the paper I
discovered he had made me an author and
I thought that was very generous of him
uh to have to have done that because it
seemed like very simple idea
and I mean very obvious vious idea and
I later realized much later that it was
not an obvious idea to most people
uh and that that had actually impressed
uh Dystra
when that was the only thing I actually
did with Dystra many years later he said
that I had uh a remarkable ability at
abstraction
only in very recent years I mean Maybe
maybe after I got the touring award that
I realized that the reason for my
success and the reason I got it wind up
wound up getting a touring award was not
that I was particularly that smart but
that I had this gift of abstraction and
Dystra
was smart enough to realize that I was
invited to uh spend a month uh but not
with Dysterra, with a colleague of his,
Carl Carl Holton. Only one thing that
was ever published came out of that.
Carl and I would uh meet with Dystra
once a week. Uh in the in the course of
that discussion, the idea somehow came
up that led to uh a variant of the
bakery algorithm that I wrote up and
published. Uh so that was the the one
tangible result that that came from my
month in uh the Netherlands.
>> Yeah. I I saw that you wrote that. Yeah.
You you spent one afternoon a week
working, talking and drinking beer at
Dextrous House and you kind of don't
remember exactly who was uh you know in
charge of uh what on that paper, but
>> yeah. Well, I don't think I was really
could have gotten that drunk because uh
I probably drove to the meeting and back
from the meeting. So,
>> Right. Right.
>> The the Dutch beer that I was drinking
was not very alcoholic.
>> I wanted to talk about your most cited
paper, the one titled time clocks and
the ordering of events and distributed
systems. What's the story behind the
paper and the problem you were solving
with it?
>> The origin was simple. uh it well
somebody sent me a paper on building
distributed databases and so where
you'll have well multiple copies of the
data in different places and you need to
keep them synchronized in some way. I
looked at it and I realized that their
solution had this problem
that the se that it it had the property
that things would be executed as if they
occurred in subsequence but that
sequence could be different from the
sequence in which they actually
happened. The notion of of what you know
happening before means is not obvious or
not obvious to most people but I happen
to
you know learn about you know special
relativity in particular uh what's known
as the it's the space-time view of of
special relativity where you basically
consider space and time together just
one four-dimensional thing and that was
Einstein wrote his paper in 1905 and and
in I think it was 1909
uh somebody whose name I'm blocking on
provided this four-dimensional view and
that four-dimensional view has the the
particular notion of what it means for
one pro one event to occur before
another and that notion is that one
event happens before another. If a a
signal
uh was emitted from the first event and
received by the whoever did that second
event before that second event happened,
but the communication could not travel
faster than the speed of light because
nothing can travel faster than the speed
of light. Well, I realized there was an
obvious analogy.
Uh the notion of happens before is
exactly the same as in relativity except
instead of being whether something one
event can influence another by things
traveling at the speed of light, it's
whether the first event could have
affected the other by information sent
over messages that were actually sent in
the system. The thing that you know blew
people away was this this definition of
of happens before in a distributed
system with also this was the first
paper I would call like you know had a
scientific result about distributed
systems. I made perhaps you know mistake
that I was warned against at some point
of having two ideas in in one paper. The
other thing that I realized was that
there was an an algorithm that would
show whether one event that it would
produce an ordering that satisfied this
that condition that if some if one event
happened the other before the other then
that first event would be ordered before
the other. And I realized that if you
had an algorithm to do that, you could
use it to basically provide the the
synchronization you needed for any
distributed system
because you could describe that system
in terms of a state machine. And a state
machine as as I described it then is
something that has a state and process
executes you know uh commands that need
to be executed in order and the command
simply is something that makes a change
of the state and and produces a value.
And so you can just describe this state
machine as just you know how event how
commands affect the state and and how
they produce and what you know what the
new state is as a function of the
original state and what the value is as
a function of the original state. It it
turned out that this was very obvious to
me, but that's really in practice
the important idea in that paper
because it showed that this method of
building distributed systems by thinking
in terms of state machine and and can
thinking about concurrent systems in
terms of state machines.
Um but that part was completely ignored.
As a matter of fact, twice I talked to
people about that paper and they said
there was nothing in that paper about
state machines and I had to go back and
reread and reread the paper to be sure I
wasn't going crazy and it really did
talk about state machines. It's
important uh for another reason. uh if
you're trying to understand a concurrent
program you concurrent programs are
written the bakery algorithm is really
an exception uh concurrent programs are
written assuming atomic actions so that
you assume that the execution behaves
like a a sequence you you can assume
that the execution proceeds as a
sequence of events. It turns out that
the way to understand, you know, why why
does a program produce the right answer?
Well, the answer is well, you it you
give it the uh the you know the right
input. You give it the input and then it
produces the right answer. Well, but by
the time you're in the middle of
execution,
what it was given at the beginning is
ancient history. The only thing that
that tells the program what to do next
is its current state.
And the way to understand
uh a program, you know, a simple program
that just, you know, takes input and
produces an answer is to say what is the
property of the state at each point that
ensures that the answer it produces is
correct is going to be correct. And that
property which is mathematically a fun a
boolean valued function of the state is
called an invariant.
And understanding the invariant
is the way to understand the system. You
know the the program and I realized that
the same thing is true of concurrent
systems and concurrent programs. People
like to write proof you know behavioral
proofs reasoning about sequences.
And the problem with that is that the
number of sequences possible sequences
you know is exponential in the length of
the sequence
while the com so your complexity of your
reasoning gets to be very complicated.
It's very easy to to miss cases. Um but
the complexity of an invariance proof
the complexity of the invariant
basically
is well oh god it's the number of
possible executions is exponential in
the number of processes
but the
uh
the behavior of the proof of a an
invariance proof is quadratic in the
number of processes. you know that's
basically why invariance proofs are
better but you know there's still for a
long time that you know people you know
doing uh distributed systems theory are
trying to do it uh you know develop you
know methods and formalism something
that are based on partial orderings and
that they've you know published a lot of
papers but it's just you know not the
way if you want to do it in practice
that's that's not the way to do it and I
shouldn't say you know it's not the way
uh you know there are algorithms like
the bakery algorithm that you know you
know thinking in partial orderings is in
fact a very good way of doing it but
those are the exceptions the the work
the method that works you know that you
can be sure will will will work is the
use of invariance
>> I want to talk about the I guess the
next paper which uh is the Byzantines
general's problem. I think that's
something that we hear about and we
learn about when you're going through
college and computer science and the
name is great and I want to know the the
story behind that problem. After I wrote
that time clocks paper that was a tells
you how to build a distributed system
but assuming no failures and it was
obvious that um
you know distributed one reason for a
distributed systems is you have multiple
computers so if one fails you can you
know keep going. in particular
uh that was the problem that
it was being solved at SRRI when I uh
when I joined it but before I got to
SRRI and I started working on that
problem and I uh there's no notion of
idea of you know what I should think
about is you know what what can a
failure do so I assume that you know the
worst possible case that a failed
process might do absolutely anything.
And I came up with an algorithm that
basically would uh implement a state
machine uh
under that assumption and that the
algorithm I came out with used digital
signatures. Yeah. So that it used the
fact that a faulty process might do
anything but it could not forge the
signature of another process
>> which just means that the message can be
trusted that it came from a private
>> right so that you can relay messages and
the people know can check that the
relayed message is actually the one that
was originally sent uh and so that a
solution using that when I got to SRRI I
realized that the people were were
trying to solve the same problem. Uh but
there are two differences. First of all,
at the time I did this was you know
1975.
very few people know knew about digital
signatures and in fact I don't remember
when the Diffy Helman paper was
published but it was around 1975
and I happen to know about digital
signatures because Whit Diffy who was
one of the author two authors of that
paper uh was a friend of mine and in
fact at one point we were at a coffee
house uh and he was describing these
things that he said we have this problem
of building digital signatures uh you
know we haven't solved and I said oh
that seems easy enough and uh and I sat
down and literally on a napkin I wrote
out a a you know the first digital
signature algorithm. It was not
practical at the time because it it
required basically something like uh
you know 128 bits to sign one bit of the
you know of of the thing you they're
signing. It's not quite that bad because
you know as you might think because you
could use sign not a
the entire dent document but a hash of
that document which you assume you know
people cannot forge uh
>> the hash they can't reverse
>> yeah you can't reverse you go take a
hash and and you know you find some
other hash that you know or some other
document that satisfies that hash. But
anyway, that's why I had, you know,
digital signatures were part of my
toolkit. Uh, so the people at SRRI
didn't have that, but they also had a
nicer abstraction
of it. Instead of getting agreement on a
sequence among the processes on a
sequence of commands,
uh they would agree have an algorithm
for agreement on a single command and
then that algorithm would be uh executed
multiple times to and you know that was
a nicer way of of describing
uh you know what you're doing than than
the than than my method. So the first
paper that was published uh use gave
both the their original oh so but since
they didn't have digital
signatures they used a different
algorithm uh and they had the property
that to tolerate one faulty process uh
you needed four processes whereas if you
used digital signatures you only needed
three processes. So the original paper
contained both algorithms and so I was
one of the authors. The other algorithm
without digital signatures is is more
complicated and the general one for end
processes was really a work of genius.
Uh it was almost incomprehensible. You
just had to read in this complicated
proof that uh you know for the arbitrary
case of an arbitrary number of processes
you need n pro for to tolerate n faults
you needed four n processes whereas with
digital signatures you need three n
processes and the the algorithm for
single fault wasn't hard but the one for
multiple four parts was uh Marshall Peas
was the one who did it and just
brilliant uh Later in a in a later paper
I uh I discovered uh a simpler proof one
that was an inductive proofly proof that
if it works for n minus one you know you
it worked for n with 3 n if it works for
3 n * n minus one the original paper was
uh you know the original one was just
brilliant uh who would have discovered
it anyway um so we published that paper
and I realized that this was this the
whole idea of Byzantine fault. So the
thing is that Byzantine well Byzantine
fault is one that where process assume a
process can do anything. Now I was
assuming that you know processing can do
anything because you know I didn't know
what to assume but the people at SRRI
had the contract for building a
multipprocess multi- computer system for
flying airplanes and so they were the
ones who appreciated the need for
solving processes that can do malicious
things because they they really couldn't
assume what it would do. And every time
you would get an algorithm and you you'd
see, oh, uh, well, this algorithm, you
know, try to get an algorithm with three
processes, you know, for one fault, you
know, you'd find that, you know, oh, you
know, this this works and it must be,
you know, really couldn't happen in
practice. And then you'd be able to find
some sequence of plausible failures that
would lead the algorithm to be defeated
if there were a faulty process. So you
needed four uh and for some reason you
know I thought that digital signatures
was almost a metaphor in the algorithm
that it should be possible
you know since we weren't worried about
malicious failures but but you know just
things that happen randomly that there
should be some way of of writing a
digital signature algorithm that uh you
know would have a sufficiently low
probability of of failing but
I never worked on that and nobody else
ever did. So that those that algorithm
was was pretty much ignored because
digital signatures were very expensive
in those days. I don't know what's being
done now because you know computers are
digital signatures are just computing
and computing is you know is cheap. Uh
but uh I remember at some point I
happened to be communicating with
someone who was an engineer at Boeing
and I asked whether they knew about
those results and he said yes when that
he in fact uh was the one at Boeing who
would read that paper and his reaction
was oh we need four
four computers.
Uh but at any rate I realized that this
was an important result and it should be
well known and I had learned one thing
from Dystra.
uh Dy, you know, one of the things I
learned from Dystra, he wrote this paper
called the the dining philosophers
problem. And that paper got a lot of
attention, but the dining philosophers
problem, I won't go into what it is, but
I think the basic problem uh was not
particularly interesting, but it had a
cute story to it. It involved a bunch of
philosophers sitting around a table with
uh some funny kind of spaghetti that it
required two forks and there was one
fork between you know each fork would be
shared with two people and uh but and I
think realized it was because of that
cute story that that problem was was
popular. And so I decided that you know
this this our work needed a cute story
you know a nice story and I in invented
Byzantine generals with the idea being
that you have a group of you know for
the for the one failure case you have
four generals who have to agree whether
or not to attack. uh and if they all
attack
uh they'll win the battle. But if only
some of them attack or if even if three
of them attack they'll win the battle.
But if only two attack you know they
would lose. But one of the the generals
might be uh a traitor. And so how could
you you know solve this problem? And so
so it's phrased in terms of these
generals having to communicate and
decide whether to make the single
decision whether to uh attack or or
retreat. Um and you know I called it the
Byzantine generals uh problem.
>> I saw in your your uh notes about the
problem that there was maybe a subset of
the problem or a prior version that was
called the Chinese general's problem or
something like that.
>> Oh yeah. that yeah I was uh there was a
different problem that uh Jim Gray uh
described uh as an impossibility result
basically it's called the Chinese
generals problem and I I won't bother
going into what it is and so that gave
me the idea of generals uh I actually
initially thought of the idea of
Albanian generals because at that time
Albania was a black hole as far as the
rest of the world was concerned. It was
a communist regime, a part of the the
Soviet uh block, but it was even more
Soviet than the Soviet Republic and and
and you know, more restrictive. So
someone uh my boss said, "Well, you
know, there are Albanians in the world,
so shouldn't that so should have a
different name?" And then I I realized
that Byzantine there aren't any
Byzantiums Byzantines around and that
was the perfect name. So
>> it's interesting to me in the story that
because this isn't the first time the
problem was specified but it was the
first time that you had named it uh um
gave it a good catchy name essentially
and and uh you know added some
additional results. What was it that you
saw in that problem that made it
interesting? Or rather like how do you
know that a problem is worth putting
extra time into? Oh, well this one it
was because you know the it was obvious
that people were going to be building
that computers were going to fly our
airplane fly airplanes and the reason in
fact because was was that this was
during the the time of the oil crisis in
the 70s and that they knew people knew
that they could build more
energyefficient planes by reducing the
size the the size of the control
surfaces.
But that made the plane aerodynamically
unstable. Uh and a a pilot couldn't make
the all the adjustments needed to, you
know, to keep it flying, but a computer
could. So it was clear the future was,
you know, airplanes were going to be
flying be flown by computers as they
are, you know, today. uh and
uh people didn't realize they thought
that oh if you want to be able to
tolerate one fault you just use three
computers
and they didn't realize that you know
with arbitrary faults you need four and
so that was a really important result
and that's why I believe that it it
needed to to be well known
>> generally when you look at the problems
that you are solving with your work Um,
how'd you decide? Cuz if you're working
at a company, you can decide based off
of maybe the I guess the impact to the
company like is it going to make more
money or save cost or something like
that. But I wonder in your work across
your career um you know think about the
bakery problem or some of your later
work as well. How do you know it's it's
so open-ended. How do you know which
problems are uh the ones worthwhile?
Throughout my career, I worked for
private companies, you know, not, you
know, not in academia or or for the
government. Uh, and so some problems
arose because of, you know, sometimes,
you know, an engineer would have a
problem and come come to me. And so, uh,
you know, DIS Paxos, for example, was
was a case of that that somebody
actually wanted an algorithm to do what
it did. You mentioned earlier Paxos and
I know that's one of your your most
famous uh works. Curious about the story
behind maybe that paper and the problem
you're solving.
>> Well, the problem I was trying is
exactly the same problem as I was
solving in the the Byzantine general's
work uh basically building a a fault
tolerant state machine. But by that time
it was you know the in the faults that
interested industry were ones where
failure meant that the computer just
stopped the not not that it did
arbitrary things. So uh the paxos is an
algorithm for uh
for for building fault tolerance systems
for handling that class of faults. uh
and
the people I was working at was which
the it was the deck circ
was in which I joined in 1985 and they
built a
uh
one of the first operating systems that
uh was a a distributed operating system.
Uh so that
um basically everybody had the they
basically these are the people who had
come from Xerox Park and had invented
personal computing but they also had the
notion of distributed personal computing
and they invented the Ethernet uh you
know for that. So they basically all of
the uh computers in the building were on
a single Ethernet network and shared a
common storage uh and they had an
algorithm for maintaining consistency of
that storage and I didn't believe well
they didn't have an algorithm they had
an operating system with code that did
that um and
I didn't believe that what they what
they did was possible. Uh,
namely I I didn't think um
well I forget exactly why I didn't think
it was possible but at any rate I
started you know trying to uh come up
with a a an impossibility proof and
start solidity proof well and an
algorithm to solve this would have to do
this and in order to do this it would
have to do that and at some point I
stopped and said oh this isn't a proof.
It it can't. This is an algorithm that
does it.
>> You said that they had code but not an
algorithm.
>> Yeah.
>> Um what do you mean by that? when most
people sit down and start writing
programs that you know they start by
thinking in terms of code
and one of the things I learned fairly
early in my career I don't remember
exactly when that back in in the days
when I started writing algorithms people
talked about people were calling them
programs and I was probably calling them
programs too I mean I remember then at
some point I realized that that wasn't
wasn't talking about programs. I was
talking about al interested in
algorithms.
Uh and an algorithm is something that's
more abstract than a pro than than a
program. U an algorithm can be you know
a program is written in in some
particular code. But an algorithm can be
implemented if programs written in any
any kinds of code. It's it's something
that's that's at a higher level of of of
abstraction. And of course I like that
because abstraction is something I'm I
was good at, you know, even without
realizing that that's what I was doing.
Uh
and so
what I've spent a large part of my
career basically from maybe about you
know 2000 or so onward uh was
getting people who build concurrent
systems
uh to not just write code but to have an
algorithm. Now a system does lots of
things but there should be some kernel
of the of the program that's that's
involved with synchronizing the
different processes
or the distributed system the different
computers and that code
you know is very hard to get you know
the you know that correct so you you
don't want to think in terms of code
because static coding, you know,
conflates, you know, a lot of issues
that are irrelevant to the concurrency
aspect. And so you should be thinking,
you know, first get an algorithm that
does that synchronization and then
implement that algorithm. I was looking
at the Paxos paper and uh some of your
notes about it and I saw that um there's
a there's an eight-year gap between when
you came up with the algorithm and when
the the paper was actually published
called Part-Time Parliament is the name
of the paper. Why why is there an
eight-year gap? Oh, well
the re the referees originally said well
this paper is okay you know not terribly
important but fortunately Butler Lamson
realized the importance of the algorithm
and together with the idea of you know I
guess you can implement anything because
it's implementing a state machine uh and
you know went about proceed uh
procilitizing
uh building your systems you know using
paxos uh you know and and thinking in
terms of state machines and uh so you
know I wasn't uh so the idea was getting
out so you know I was in no hurry to
publish so you know I just let the paper
sit and eventually uh there was a new
editor that came along and uh
uh
he said that you know I think the status
of the paper was that it was just uh you
know it had been accepted but had no and
needed revision and uh so he decided
that yeah let's you know to to publish
it and uh it was eventually published
with little some a few things that uh to
take well to to mention work that had
been done in the in the in the uh
interim and what I got is uh got a Keith
Marzulo uh you know to do that part for
me. Uh and uh so the story was that this
manuscript this was that well the story
about Paxos was that you know was a this
happened you know centuries ago and you
know this manuscript and uh I used that
to the effect that you know when
something you know the tales of
something were I considered obvious and
you know not interesting you know the
the paper would say it's not clear how
the Paxons what the Paxons did you know
at this point but Um at any rate and uh
so uh
and Keith you know kept up the that idea
that you know this was a you know a
description of this ancient thing and
and he wrote a you know a little prefix
or a preface or something to to it and
uh you know added maybe I think some uh
references. I saw in your writing too
when you were talking about presenting
the paper initially,
>> you even uh dressed up in like an
Indiana Jones style archaeologist. Well,
how did that go when you presented about
this Paxos uh paper and algorithm?
>> Well, I think the the lecture may have
gone well, but uh I think nobody
understood the algorithm where nobody
understood the significance of the
algorithm.
>> It sounds like no one understood it
except for Butler Lamson. What what did
he see that made him unique? I guess.
>> Well, he had a good understanding of
building systems, you know, he really
deserved his touring award. He was one
of the original people at Xerox Park who
were building distributed uh personal
computing.
He and Chuck Thacker, I think, were
probably the two senior people, you
know, in that lab. I saw later there was
a paper which describes a new algorithm
which seems to solve the same problem.
The raft paper. I was wondering if you
read that and what your thoughts were on
on that versus Paxos. The authors of
that actually sent me a draft of the
original paper and I looked at it and
said uh I forget whether I said send it
back to me when you have an algorithm or
send that back to me when you have a
proof. I I forget which one it was and
uh you got the idea and they really they
they did write you know add a proof in
the paper or not. Uh yeah and I never
read future later versions and someone
whose judgment I value said you know had
read it and said that it's basically
it's it's the Paxos paper but no but
with some of the the tales left
unfinished by the Paxos paper uh by uh
you know filled some of the tales filled
in but they you know described it in a
in a very different Hey, the basic idea
of the what Paxos works is it's two
phases and you're trying to implement a
sequence of you know of decisions and it
turns out you can do the first phase
once
for a whole it involves a leader. So um
and the leader has to get elected. Uh so
but it turns out that you can do the
first uh phase once
uh and you don't have to do it again as
long as you have the same leader. Uh but
it's only the second part that you have
to do and then you have to elect the the
new leader if a new leader fails and do
the first part. So think about it in
those two phases. But the way people the
way engineers you know like to think
about it is well you do this you know
you talking about the first part the the
second phase you keep doing this uh
until the leader fa fails and then you
go back then you have to do this thing
so it's explaining it in the in the
opposite order uh and in fact you know
when you start it from from fresh the uh
you don't have to do the first uh uh the
first phase you can you basically what
what's done in the first phase could be
just built in into the initial state but
you know I think that that's the right
you know of those two phases the way to
understand it uh but you know the raft
people also had this idea that you know
raft is better because it's simpler and
I I must say that a lot of people say
that uh Paxos is hard to understand and
I don't understand why. I mean, I've
explained it to some people in five
minutes and they understood it. At any
rate, the raft people said that one of
the ideas were simpler because and they
even have, you know, taught, you know,
Paxos to one class and and uh the raft
to another and they took and then yes,
the people all the students said that
yes, it was more understandable. Uh the
interesting thing about it though is
that uh there was a bug discovered in
raft and fixed but I believe that the
algorithm that they found more
understandable was one with that bug.
So uh made me realize that uh you know
what most people you know what does
understanding mean and for me
understanding means you know you can
write a proof of it but what
understanding means for most people is
warm fuzzy feeling and you know the raft
description gave them you know more of a
warm fuzzy feeling because you know you
know that that was seems to be the way
you know programmers, you know, like to
think about the the algorithm, you know,
you know, the second phase, you know,
first until, you know, you get a failure
and uh
but the way I describe it is one that
helps you get a better understanding of
why it actually works.
>> So, yeah, we talked about a lot of your
papers. I know one of your other uh
contributions whether you knew it or not
at the time was latte and uh building
that and something that has impacted the
entire academic community. What's the
story behind wanting to build latte?
>> Oh, that was uh very simple. Um,
I was wanted I was in the process of
starting to write a book and uh
it was clear that tech was the basic uh
type setting system that one had to use.
But you know I felt that I would need
macros uh to make tech do what I wanted
it to do. And uh so
I decide figured with uh been a little
extra effort uh I could make the macros
usable by other people. The system I had
been using before tech it's called
scribe and uh that really had the basic
idea of scribe was that
you describe the logical structure of of
the document
not and the
and scribe will do the formatting. Well,
scribe didn't do that great a job of
formatting. Uh so, uh but
obviously, you know, I like the idea
abstraction that it's the ideas that
matter, not the text that ma, you know,
the the writing that matters, not the
type setting. And so,
um, I actually
at some point, uh, I met Peter Gordon,
Addison Wesley, uh, I'm not sure what
what you would call him, but he looks
for, you know, books to publish. And,
uh, he convinced me that I should write
a book on it. And those days, it never
occurred to me people would actually
spend money for a book about software.
But you know what the hell? And what he
did was he introduced me to uh a
typographic designer at uh Addison
Wesley who was responsible for really
for the typographic design that's in the
standard uh latex styles. You know,
basically I just did that in my quote
spare time. You know, took me six or
nine months or so. I I suppose the uh
statute of limitations has run out, but
I was really, you know, spent some time
working on that when I was allegedly,
you know, billing the time to some
project that had nothing to do with it.
>> On the topic of writing, you have a
quote that I really enjoy. It's if
you're if you're thinking without
writing, you only think you're thinking.
And I was curious to hear your thoughts
on what you mean by that.
>> Well, it was really meant for, you know,
people building computer systems. You
have an idea and you think it's going to
work. Uh or you have something that, you
know, you think is something that
somebody else will you want to use.
Well, write a description of it. Uh
there's an old maxim that I don't I
heard uh that is you know write the
instruction manual before you write the
program. a great advice. Uh I did not do
that uh with latte but it I definitely
when I was writing the book and I
discovered that something was hard to to
describe hard to explain that needed to
be changed and I made you know a number
of uh of changes to it uh as a result of
that but uh I didn't start at the
beginning with the instruction manual.
Why is writing conducive to good
thinking?
>> Because it's very easy to
uh
it's very easy to fool yourself.
Uh I mean that underlies my uh my whole
idea of of writing proofs. One thing I
learned is that you had to write a a
correctness proof of an concurrent
algorithm.
And when my algorithm was starting to
get more complicated,
the proofs started I started writ
PhD in math. I knew how to write proofs
and I was starting writing the proofs
the way I would normally do. And I
realized it just didn't work because
there were just so many details involved
and I just couldn't keep track of them
and whether I had done it. And so as a
computer science know how to deal with
concurrency
uh it's hierarchical structure and so I
devised this hierarchical structure
where a proof is uh you know is a
sequence of steps each of which has a
proof and the proof is either a par well
a proof is either a paragraph or a
statement a sequence of steps each with
its proof and that proof can be either a
parag graph or a sequence of steps with
its proof and you know so you break the
whole problem up into these smaller
pieces. So there's never any question of
you know where is this coming from. You
know you're stating that this step
follows from you know this step this
step this step this step and if it does
not follow from that step your proof is
wrong. The theorem might be correct but
but means your proof is wrong. Um well
you know so I've discovered that worked
great on writing my proofs of programs
but I decided to really you know I also
write proofs of theorems you know you
know uh you know think proofs that are
things that are you know more like
ordinary math and I started trying that
on them and I discovered it worked
beautifully. So when I started to to try
to convince mathematicians to write
these proofs uh I started in one small
seminar I went you know won't describe
what it was about but uh and I I
described this this proof through maybe
uh 20 mathematicians or something their
reaction shocked me
they became angry
I really thought that they might
physically attack me. So
I believe that what's going on is that
when pe I mean I believe that's totally
irrational and when people act
irrationally
it tends to be out of fear
and what I believe people are afraid of
is that mathematicians are afraid of is
that they're going to have to write
their proofs to convince a a computer
program and and in fact you know and I
give it a one of those talks I gave you
know I say very clearly this doesn't
have to be you don't have to be any more
formal than you do you can write the
exact same thing proof you know but it's
just a matter of organizing things and
it's very simple you know hierarchical
structure and then when you're using a
fact mention that you're using that
nothing about formalism or anything you
know after I gave that talk someone got
up and said I don't want to have to
write my proof my my proofs for a
computer program.
And in fact, it's more work doing that
because the reason it's more work is
that it reveals what you haven't said
and that there's steps in there that you
know, you may think they're obvious, but
you haven't written them down.
And if you believe something is correct
but don't really if you if you think you
know something but don't write it down,
you only think you know it. And that's
where errors come in. You know, that's
where that one-third of your paper's
errors can, you know, you know, uh, come
in because it really makes you honest.
When I look across your career, I think
you had a lot of contributions people
might expect might come from academia,
these papers and things, but you did uh
all of your work in industry. Why did
you not see yourself as a academic and
more of uh working for industry? Well, I
started out programming
uh and I eventually got jobs where took
me into what we now call computer
science. At the time I never even
realized that uh there was you know
there could be a computer a science of
computing. Uh it wasn't until you know
maybe until
mid to late '7s that I realized yes
there was a computer science and know as
a computer scientist. Um but it never
seemed to me that like computer science
was a an academic subject. At some point
I, you know, had to make a choice
between doing computer science and
without calling it computer science or
or teaching math at a at a university.
And I I chose for random fairly random
reasons to you do computer science. Uh
so it you know for the first
I don't know
well till maybe the mid80s or something
it just didn't seem to me that you know
you know computer science was something
that people needed to go to to a
university to learn. And uh I suppose
afterwards that I was sort of I guess I
I just didn't think it would be fun
teaching computer science. So
>> I saw in your your writing you had a
footnote that said somewhere that you
you you felt like a a failure at some
point because you you wanted to develop
this grand theory of concurrency and you
never discovered it. Um do do you still
feel that way or what are your thoughts
on that that footnote? lots of people
who you know a large percentage of the
people who were doing things like I was
doing which is not a large number of
people uh there's this notion that uh
they're looking for the touring machine
of concurrency you know the touring
machine was this abstraction which
really captured what computing was
uh and
they were looking for something that
would be the you know the touring
machine of of
concurrent computing
and
you know nobody succeeded. I mean there
are some people who think they've
succeeded. Uh the patronets are are
something that uh I guess I don't have
time to to explain but uh there was a
big it was big in the 70s. Uh, and I was
actually surprised to think that there's
still a large community of people doing
uh, patriets. But what I now realize is
that patriets and
most of the things that people were
doing was really language-based.
And I was never interested in languages.
I'm interested in what the language is
expressing.
And you know I realized in some sense
you know maybe I've realized what the
touring machine of of of computing is
state machines. Uh state machines are a
little bit different the way I now
describe them. They don't have commands.
They just have a state and a and a next
state relation. Uh even simpler than
talking about commands and and and
values and stuff. Uh and you know to me
you know that's the uh that's the
touring machine of of con of concurrency
but it
uh it it doesn't have the function that
that touring machines offer because it
it doesn't what touring machines do is
uh describe what's you know what's
possible
uh and state machines can describe
anything
including things that are not possible.
Uh and and in fact uh the there's a good
reason for that. Um
for example
uh when I describe a uh an algorithm I
will talk about you know the values of a
variable you know can be any integer.
Now you can implement the program where
you have any integer
uh but that makes the but talking about
you know computer integers would
complicate things unnecessarily.
The people have this funny idea that you
know because something is infinite it's
more complicated. They got it backwards.
Infinity was introduced to simplify
things. You know the first thing you
learn is arithmetic.
You're learning arithmetic with an
infinite number of integers because if
you restricted to a finite set of
integers, arithmetic becomes much more
complicated.
So you know the abstractions of
mathematics
uh which people find you know because
they don't have the proper training in
mathematics find you know difficult uh
are really what's simplifying things and
that's what you what you use this
mathematics the state machine is
described for me by me using mathematics
that's the right you know the the most
powerful way of doing
But
computer people and computer scientists
and programmers are really hung up on
languages
and so they are looking for you know
they invent all sorts of languages and
they're all describable and in fact if
you want to give them a semantics you
would do it in terms of a state machine
and they just think that this uh you
know this language ES improves your
thinking.
uh it doesn't you may I mean there are
reasons why you use computer languages
and you don't write your your programs
code in math and they involve basically
efficiency
but for understanding you know you can't
build math you can't beat math and you
know attempts to uh do it by something
that looks like a programming language
uh is is just the wrong way to to to
deal when you're trying to deal with
concurrency.
>> When I look at uh everything that you've
written and all the stories, there's
these little anecdotes. There's things
where you say things like you you never
considered yourself smart, but you
noticed that other kids had an awful
time understanding things or yeah,
there's a problem that you solved where
someone else had difficulties, but you
don't view your contribution as a
brilliant one or anything like that. And
that that uh doesn't connect with me
because you've also won a touring award
and done all these amazing things. So,
how could that be that you, you know,
just merely discover things and are are
not smart yet you've achieved so much?
>> Well, this general thing that, you know,
psychologists talk about uh is that when
someone is good at something, they don't
realize how they're good they are at it
because it's simple to them.
There's the opposite one that uh people
who are bad at something think they're
better than they are because they're bad
at it.
Or to put uh a little bit more
concisely,
stupid people think they're smart
because they're too stupid to realize
they're not. Uh my the gift that I have
is not in some sense raw intelligence.
It's abstraction
and it's only recently, you know, the
last 10 or so years
that I realized how much better I am at
that than other people, most other
people. At this point, you've
experienced so much and you when you
look back on your career. If you could
go back to yourself when you just
graduated college and give yourself some
advice knowing what you know now, what
would you say?
>> One thing I've learned fairly early in
my life is that I shouldn't waste time
trying to answer questions that I don't
have to answer.
I don't think about, you know, what I
should have done because uh that's a
question that I don't have to answer.
>> Thank you for listening to the podcast.
It's a passion project of mine that I've
really enjoyed building. Another passion
project that I've been working on kind
of in secret is building an ergonomic
keyboard that I wish existed and I
finally have a prototype. So, I'd love
to show you what we've built. It's ultra
low profile and ergonomic. and I
couldn't find anything like it on the
market. So, that's why we built it. I'll
put a link to the keyboard in the
description. You can take a look and
learn more about the project there. We
could definitely use your support. Also,
if you have any feedback for me about
the show, I'd love to hear it. Comments
on YouTube have led to guests coming on
like Ilia Gregoric and David Fowler. I
wasn't aware of them until someone
dropped a comment. Also, feedback in the
comments helped me learn to reduce the
number of cliffhers in the intros. So,
your comments definitely make a
difference. Please keep letting me know
what you'd like to see more of in the
show, and I'll see you in the next
episode.